Guide to the John Penley Photographs and Papers TAM.501
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Penley Photographs and Papers
circa 1980-2013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Penley, John.
TAM.501
15.5 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 oversize flat box, 9 photograph boxes, and 10 negative boxes
John Penley is a photographer and grassroots political activist associated with the squatters' rights movement and housing protests of the 1980s and 1990s in New York City's East Village and Lower East Side. The collection primarily consists of Penley's photographic materials (mainly prints and negatives) dating mostly from the 1990s that document gentrification and protests relating to housing rights in the Lower East Side and throughout New York City. Other social issues addressed by Penley's photographs include AIDS and gay rights activism and activism against police brutality, the death penalty, and racial hate crimes and discrimination.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Penley in 2009; additional materials were donated in 2013. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2009.007, 2009.041, NPA.2009.004, NPA.2009.008, 2013.014, and 2013.019.
Arrangement note
This collection has been arranged into two series:
Series I: Papers, circa 1980-2010
Series II: Photographs, circa 1980-2013
Series I is organized alphabetically by folder title. Series II is physically arranged by format and intellectually arranged sequentially by an archivist-supplied alphanumeric code indicating a discrete event or photo shoot. For more information on this arrangement system, please refer to the Processing Information Note. The subseries John Penley 2013 Donation was included in series II to reflect additional material incorporated into the collection in 2013.
Biographical/Historical note
John Penley is a photographer and grassroots political activist associated with the squatters' rights movement and housing protests of the 1980s and 1990s in New York City's East Village and Lower East Side, as well as numerous other social causes. A former Navy serviceman, Penley took up photography as part of an effort to document the demonstrations, protests, and other political actions in which he took part, and in the process became a photojournalist. Hundreds of Penley's photographs have appeared in in publications including the New York Daily News, the New York Post, the New York Times, New York and Long Island Newsday, New York Magazine, The Villager, High Times Magazine, The Guardian, Art In America, WW 3 Illustrated, The Shadow, the East Village Eye, and many small political publications. They have also been distributed through press services such as United Press International and the Associated Press.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Related Archival Materials note
Researchers interested in squatters' rights may also wish to consult the following collections at the Tamiment Library:
Squatters' Rights Collection: Fly Papers (TAM 363)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Jane Churchman Papers (TAM 313)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Jerry "The Peddler" Wade (TAM 366)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Kurt Reynertson Papers (TAM 335)
Squatters' Rights Collection: On Davis Papers (TAM 365)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Peter Spagnuolo Papers (TAM 336)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Roland Politi Papers (TAM 364)
Scope and Contents note
The collection primarily consists of Penley's photographic materials (mainly prints and negatives) dating mostly from the 1990s that document gentrification and protests relating to housing rights in the Lower East Side and throughout New York City. Other social issues addressed by Penley's photographs include AIDS and gay rights activism and activism against police brutality, the death penalty, and racial hate crimes and discrimination. To a lesser extent, the collection also contains magazine and newspaper clippings that feature Penley's photographs, leaflets and handbills related to the squatters' rights movement, and legal documents concerning Penley's 1982 and 1987 arrests. An additional set of photographs taken 2009-2013 also contains images relating to life in the Lower East Side as well as Occupy Wall Street and protests in support of Chelsea Manning and Wikileaks.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Separated Materials
Some personal photographs were returned to the donor.
Gay rights -- New York (State) -- New York.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.).; AIDS (Disease) |x Political aspects |z New York (State) |z New York.; Homelessness; Squatters -- New York (State) -- New York; Slides (photographs); Negatives (photographic); Race discrimination -- United States.; Police brutality.; Documentary photography |z New York (State) |z New York.; Marijuana -- Therapeutic use.; Tompkins Square Park (New York, N.Y.); Photographs.; Photographers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Penley, John.; ACT UP New York (Organization); Housing Works, Inc
- Series I: Papers, circa 1980-2010; 467090
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I contains magazine and newspaper clippings that feature Penley's photographs or are related to his photographic and journalistic interests, as well as leaflets and handbills (including some original artwork) concerning the squatters rights movement. Legal documents from Penley's suit against the New York City Police Department and then Mayor Edward Koch relating to Penley's 1987 arrest (at a rally he organized to register homeless people to vote) are also included, as are Freedom of Information Act documents and Penley's 1991 New York City Police Department press pass. There is also also a file of legal documents relating to Penley's 1982 arrest and sentencing for trespassing at the Savannah River nuclear power plant in South Carolina, as part of an anti-nuclear movement protest.
  - Arrest of Penley and His Suit Against the Mayor and the Police in Connection: Legal Documents, circa 1980-2000; 467093 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings with Penley Photos or Related to His Life and Work, circa 1980-2000; 467094 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Criminal Trespassing, Rivervale Nuclear Plant, South Carolina: Clippings, circa 1980-2000; 467095 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Criminal Trespassing, Rivervale Nuclear Plant, South Carolina: Legal Documents, circa 1980-2000; 467096 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Freedom of Information Act Requests and Other Related Material, circa 1980-2000; 467097 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Leaflets, Handbills, and Posters, circa 1980-2000; 467098 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Leaflets and Original Artwork, circa 1980-2000; 467099 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publications with Penley's Photographs, circa 1980-2000; 467100 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Working Press Pass Issued by New York Police Department, circa 1980-2000; 467101 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newspapers and Magazines, circa 1980-2010; 467102 (Box 2)
- Series II: Photographs, circa 1980-2013; 466650
  Scope and Contents note
  John Penley's images in Series II primarily document gentrification and protests relating to housing rights in New York's Lower East Side during the 1990s. However, the photographic materials in the collection (mainly prints and negatives, though there are also slides, contact sheets, and images on CD) date from the 1980s to 2013 and also showcase a variety of other social issues and feature New York City as a whole, as well as other national and international locales.
  Penley's photographs provide documentation of protests by homeless and squatters' rights activists, as well as gay rights and AIDS activists (including the organization ACT UP) and demonstrations against police brutality, the death penalty, and racial hate crimes and discrimination. Many protests Penley documented take place at political conventions and/or are against specific politicians. There are also images of medical marijuana rallies, cultural celebrations, and New York City landmarks and nightlife. Well-known individuals featured in the collection include Rudy Guiliani, Ed Koch, Al Sharpton, Jesse Jackson, Arlo Guthrie, Matt Dillon, Martin Sheen, Philip Berrigan, Timothy Leary, and Ramsey Clark, as well as Lower East Side artist and writer residents such as Allen Ginsburg, William Burroughs, Keith Haring, and Karen Finley.
  Penley documented his travels to Mexico and Nicaragua (the latter during the conflict between the Sandinista government and the "contras") during the 1980s. Two CDs contain photographs from Penley's March 2013 protest in front of New York University's Bobst Library, in which Penley attempted to persuade NYU to provide housing for the East Village's homeless and low-income residents. The series also includes three unlabeled mini-DV cassette tapes.
  Researchers should note that additional images from the same shoots and events found in the in the Tamiment Library's 2009 flickr exhibit of John Penley's images may also be found in shoots with similar captions and dates throughout the rest of the series.
  Researchers should also note that not all of the series is described. Some entire boxes of negatives or photographs are undescribed (which is noted in the container list), and occasionally a few individual shoots or events in a box are undescribed, even if the majority of the box has been described.
  - Negatives From Which Images Were Selected for Tamiment Library's 2009 Flickr Exhibit, circa 1990-2000; 467091 (Box 3, Box 4)
  - Negatives From Which Images Were Selected for Tamiment Library's 2009 Flickr Exhibit and Slides 001-S to 049-S (includes slides housed with 623-N and 664-P), circa 1990-2000; 467092 (Box 5)
  - NY Tattoo Convention, Roseland Ballroom, Paul Booth World Famous Tattoo Artist, circa 1993; 467087 (Box 13, Folder 001-N)
  - NY Tattoo Convention, Roseland Ballroom, Paul Booth World Famous Tattoo Artist, circa 1993; 467086 (Box 6, Folder 001-P)
  - Tai Chi Performance, Tompkins Square Park, Johanny's Barber Shop, circa 1995; 467085 (Box 13, Folder 002-N)
  - Tai Chi Performance, Tompkins Square Park, Johanny's Barber Shop, circa 1995; 467084 (Box 6, Folder 002-P)
  - Wigstock on Chelsea Pier, Lady Miss Kier (Deelite), 1998; 467083 (Box 13, Folder 003-N)
  - Wigstock on Chelsea Pier, Lady Miss Kier (Deelite), 1998; 467082 (Box 6, Folder 003-P)
  - Refuse and Resist at the Palladium, Mass Arrest of Squatters at Community Board 3 Meeting, Cooper Union (1 photo), Reclaim the Streets Arrests, 1993; 467081 (Box 13, Folder 004-N)
  - Refuse and Resist at the Palladium, Mass Arrest of Squatters at Community Board 3 Meeting, Cooper Union (1 photo), Reclaim the Streets Arrests, 1993; 467080 (Box 6, Folder 004-P)
  - Invest in Youth for a Safer Future Conference with Famous Politician, circa 1990-2000; 467079 (Box 13, Folder 005-N)
  - Invest in Youth for a Safer Future Conference with Famous Politician, circa 1990-2000; 467078 (Box 6, Folder 005-P)
  - Fire Island Trip, circa 1990-2000; 467077 (Box 13, Folder 006-N)
  - Fire Island Trip, circa 1990-2000; 467076 (Box 6, Folder 006-P)
  - Art Show at Hotel 17, Famous Blonde Transexual Amanda Lapore, circa 1990-2000; 467075 (Box 13, Folder 007-N)
  - Art Show at Hotel 17, Famous Blonde Transexual Amanda Lapore, circa 1990-2000; 467074 (Box 6, Folder 007-P)
  - Eviction of Adam Purple building Felton Davis of Catholic Worker arrested, 1990; 467073 (Box 13, Folder 008-N)
  - Eviction of Adam Purple building Felton Davis of Catholic Worker arrested, 1990; 467072 (Box 6, Folder 008-P)
  - Memorial for Jerry Garcia of Grateful Dead, Richie Havens performs at it Central Park, circa 1990-2000; 467071 (Box 13, Folder 009-N)
  - Memorial for Jerry Garcia of Grateful Dead, Richie Havens performs at it Central Park, circa 1990-2000; 467070 (Box 6, Folder 009-P)
  - Street Kid Musicians Acapulco Mexico, circa 1990-2000; 467069 (Box 13, Folder 010-N)
  - Street Kid Musicians Acapulco Mexico, circa 1990-2000; 467068 (Box 6, Folder 010-P)
  - Tenant Power Pataki protest Michael Shenker arrest South Street Seaport, circa 1990-2000; 467067 (Box 13, Folder 011-N)
  - Tenant Power Pataki protest Michael Shenker arrest South Street Seaport, circa 1990-2000; 467066 (Box 6, Folder 011-P)
  - Tenant protest Pataki Joel Myers arrest, Ruth Messinger Borough president speaks at protest, circa 1990-2000; 467065 (Box 13, Folder 012-N)
  - Tenant protest Pataki Joel Myers arrest, Ruth Messinger Borough president speaks at protest, circa 1990-2000; 467064 (Box 6, Folder 012-P)
  - C Town supermarket fire Ave C, circa 1990-2000; 467063 (Box 13, Folder 013-N)
  - C Town supermarket fire Ave C, circa 1990-2000; 467062 (Box 6, Folder 013-P)
  - Living Theater benefit Judith Malina, Hannon Resnikof, circa 1990-2000; 467061 (Box 13, Folder 014-N)
  - Living Theater benefit Judith Malina, Hannon Resnikof, circa 1990-2000; 467060 (Box 6, Folder 014-P)
  - Rent Strike protest, Marguerita Lopez councilperson East Village, circa 1990-2000; 467059 (Box 13, Folder 016-N)
  - Rent Strike protest, Marguerita Lopez councilperson East Village, circa 1990-2000; 467058 (Box 6, Folder 016-P)
  - Law and Order tv show notice of filming poster, shots of Mexico, circa 1990-2000; 467057 (Box 13, Folder 017-N)
  - Law and Order tv show notice of filming poster, shots of Mexico, circa 1990-2000; 467056 (Box 6, Folder 017-P)
  - Medical marijuana protest Suzis restaurant west village Dana Beal, Penny Arcade, Catholic Good Friday Easter parade East village, circa 1990-2000; 467055 (Box 13, Folder 018-N)
  - Medical marijuana protest Suzis restaurant west village Dana Beal, Penny Arcade, Catholic Good Friday Easter parade East village, circa 1990-2000; 467054 (Box 6, Folder 018-P)
  - Pataki protest south street seaport Ruth Messinger, Squatter Michael Shenker, circa 1990-2000; 467053 (Box 13, Folder 019-N)
  - Pataki protest south street seaport Ruth Messinger, Squatter Michael Shenker, circa 1990-2000; 467052 (Box 6, Folder 019-P)
  - Black Panther Dhrouba Bin Wahad, circa 1990-2000; 467051 (Box 13, Folder 020-N)
  - Black Panther Dhrouba Bin Wahad, circa 1990-2000; 467050 (Box 6, Folder 020-P)
  - NYC Tattoo Convention Hiroshi Ito famous Japanese tattoo artist, circa 1990-2000; 467049 (Box 13, Folder 021-N)
  - NYC Tattoo Convention Hiroshi Ito famous Japanese tattoo artist, circa 1990-2000; 467048 (Box 6, Folder 021-P)
  - Allen Ginsberg reads poetry at Tompkins Square Park, 1993; 467047 (Box 6, Folder 022-P)
  - Allen Ginsberg reads poetry at Tompkins Square Park, 1993; 469138 (Box 13, Folder 022-N)
  - Stonewall riot reunion march Barbara Robin Lee topless black woman squatter, circa 1990-2000; 467046 (Box 13, Folder 023-N)
  - Stonewall riot reunion march Barbara Robin Lee topless black woman squatter, circa 1990-2000; 467045 (Box 6, Folder 023-P)
  - Mayor Rudy Guiliani at public school kids event with kids and other politicians, circa 1990-2000; 467044 (Box 13, Folder 024-N)
  - Mayor Rudy Guiliani at public school kids event with kids and other politicians, circa 1990-2000; 467043 (Box 6, Folder 024-P)
  - Crime Scene of second ave deli owner murder, Italian American protest at Village Voice, circa 1990-2000; 467042 (Box 13, Folder 025-N)
  - Crime Scene of second ave deli owner murder, Italian American protest at Village Voice, circa 1990-2000; 467041 (Box 6, Folder 025-P)
  - Armando Perez Charas rally, Felton Davis Catholic worker with adopted son in stroller, circa 1990-2000; 467040 (Box 13, Folder 026-N)
  - Armando Perez Charas rally, Felton Davis Catholic worker with adopted son in stroller, circa 1990-2000; 467039 (Box 6, Folder 026-P)
  - East Village council woman Margurita Lopez with poster of LES public housing locations, circa 1990-2000; 467038 (Box 13, Folder 027-N)
  - East Village council woman Margurita Lopez with poster of LES public housing locations, circa 1990-2000; 467037 (Box 6, Folder 027-P)
  - Movie shoot at Most Holy Redeemer church E 3rd st., circa 1990-2000; 467036 (Box 13, Folder 028-N)
  - Movie shoot at Most Holy Redeemer church E 3rd st., circa 1990-2000; 467035 (Box 6, Folder 028-P)
  - Tenants outside of building after LES fire, circa 1990-2000; 467034 (Box 13, Folder 029-N)
  - Tenants outside of building after LES fire, circa 1990-2000; 467033 (Box 6, Folder 029-P)
  - Anti racist skin heads party DJ Dan Rash of anti racist skins at Sophies bar 6th st bet a and b, circa 1990-2000; 467032 (Box 13, Folder 030-N)
  - Anti racist skin heads party DJ Dan Rash of anti racist skins at Sophies bar 6th st bet a and b, circa 1990-2000; 467031 (Box 6, Folder 030-P)
  - Fire with firemen and rescue, circa 1990-2000; 467030 (Box 13, Folder 031-N)
  - Fire with firemen and rescue, circa 1990-2000; 467029 (Box 6, Folder 031-P)
  - Chiapas Mexico maya kids street scenes, circa 1990-2000; 467028 (Box 13, Folder 032-N)
  - Chiapas Mexico maya kids street scenes, circa 1990-2000; 467027 (Box 6, Folder 032-P)
  - Allen Ginsberg tree dedication TSP Pedro Pietri, Clayton Patterson other poets, circa 1990-2000; 467026 (Box 13, Folder 034-N)
  - Allen Ginsberg tree dedication TSP Pedro Pietri, Clayton Patterson other poets, circa 1990-2000; 467025 (Box 6, Folder 034-P)
  - World Bank protest Washington DC, circa 1990-2000; 467024 (Box 13, Folder 035-N)
  - World Bank protest Washington DC, circa 1990-2000; 467023 (Box 6, Folder 035-P)
  - Dean Johnson CBGBs Old Greyhound bus station Jackson Tenn., circa 1990-2000; 467022 (Box 13, Folder 036-N)
  - Dean Johnson CBGBs Old Greyhound bus station Jackson Tenn., circa 1990-2000; 467021 (Box 6, Folder 036-P)
  - Squatters protest police comm. William Bratten at Gramercy park Synagogue, Bratten, squatter Uncle Don Yippie others Seth Tobocman, circa 1990-2000; 467020 (Box 13, Folder 037-N)
  - Squatters protest police comm. William Bratten at Gramercy park Synagogue, Bratten, squatter Uncle Don Yippie others Seth Tobocman, circa 1990-2000; 467019 (Box 6, Folder 037-P)
  - East Village public library event kids from Asher Levy school, circa 1990-2000; 467018 (Box 13, Folder 038-N)
  - East Village public library event kids from Asher Levy school, circa 1990-2000; 467017 (Box 6, Folder 038-P)
  - Affordable housing protest East Village many squatters, circa 1990-2000; 467016 (Box 13, Folder 041-N)
  - Affordable housing protest East Village many squatters, circa 1990-2000; 467015 (Box 6, Folder 041-P)
  - Homestead housing protest Matt Metzger with his son Matt was responsible for squatter archive in Tamiment, Michael Shenker, Joan Moossey others, 1990; 467014 (Box 13, Folder 042-N)
  - Homestead housing protest Matt Metzger with his son Matt was responsible for squatter archive in Tamiment, Michael Shenker, Joan Moossey others, 1990; 467013 (Box 6, Folder 042-P)
  - Garden protest auction by Guiliani of community garden space, circa 1990-2000; 467012 (Box 13, Folder 043-N)
  - Garden protest auction by Guiliani of community garden space, circa 1990-2000; 467011 (Box 6, Folder 043-P)
  - Former Black panther Dhrouba Bin wahad at Cures Not Wars pot protest, circa 1990-2000; 467010 (Box 13, Folder 044-N)
  - Former Black panther Dhrouba Bin wahad at Cures Not Wars pot protest, circa 1990-2000; 467009 (Box 6, Folder 044-P)
  - Democratic Convention protest Chicago ILL Uncle Sam on stilts, 1988; 467008 (Box 13, Folder 046-N)
  - Democratic Convention protest Chicago ILL Uncle Sam on stilts, 1988; 467007 (Box 6, Folder 046-P)
  - Anti Guiliani protest, KKK and anti KKK protesters Foley Square Ron Kuby, 1988; 467006 (Box 13, Folder 047-N)
  - Anti Guiliani protest, KKK and anti KKK protesters Foley Square Ron Kuby, 1988; 467005 (Box 6, Folder 047-P)
  - Free Mumia Abu Jamal protest Dhrouba Bin Wahad with bullhorn, Grandpa Al Leweis of the Munsters tv show and WBAI, Ron Kuby, 1990; 467004 (Box 13, Folder 048-N)
  - Free Mumia Abu Jamal protest Dhrouba Bin Wahad with bullhorn, Grandpa Al Leweis of the Munsters tv show and WBAI, Ron Kuby, 1990; 467003 (Box 6, Folder 048-P)
  - LES eviction housing lawyer Jackie Buchowski SP ?, 1990; 467002 (Box 13, Folder 049-N)
  - LES eviction housing lawyer Jackie Buchowski SP ?, 1990; 467001 (Box 6, Folder 049-P)
  - Save ABC NO RIO anti Guiliani protest with Rolando Politti, Michael Shenker, Seth Tobocman, Democratic National convention protest Chicago, circa 1990-2000; 467000 (Box 14, Folder 050-N)
  - Save ABC NO RIO anti Guiliani protest with Rolando Politti, Michael Shenker, Seth Tobocman, Democratic National convention protest Chicago, circa 1990-2000; 466999 (Box 7, Folder 050-P)
  - Puerto Rican squatter pioneer Rafael Bueno arrested, circa 1990-2000; 466998 (Box 14, Folder 051-N)
  - Puerto Rican squatter pioneer Rafael Bueno arrested, circa 1990-2000; 466997 (Box 7, Folder 051-P)
  - Local 246 Union protest at construction site LES, Lach with Kiss T at TSP Lach started anti folk movement, Puerto Rican hardcore band Riccanstruction in TSP, undated; 466996 (Box 14, Folder 052-N)
  - Local 246 Union protest at construction site LES, Lach with Kiss T at TSP Lach started anti folk movement, Puerto Rican hardcore band Riccanstruction in TSP, undated; 466995 (Box 7, Folder 052-P)
  - Punk rock show Tompkins Square, circa 1990-2000; 466994 (Box 14, Folder 053-N)
  - Punk rock show Tompkins Square, circa 1990-2000; 466993 (Box 7, Folder 053-P)
  - Free Mumia Abu Jamal protest Philadelphia with Pam Africa, Bob Lederer many of the Move people who were bombed in Philly by Mayor Daily, 1993; 466992 (Box 14, Folder 054-N)
  - Free Mumia Abu Jamal protest Philadelphia with Pam Africa, Bob Lederer many of the Move people who were bombed in Philly by Mayor Daily, 1993; 466991 (Box 7, Folder 054-P)
  - West Village kids soccer team awards party, circa 1990-2000; 466990 (Box 14, Folder 055-N)
  - West Village kids soccer team awards party, circa 1990-2000; 466989 (Box 7, Folder 055-P)
  - Union protest against non union construction site in East Village, 1994; 466988 (Box 14, Folder 056-N)
  - Union protest against non union construction site in East Village, 1994; 466987 (Box 7, Folder 056-P)
  - Junkies Suck grafitti, Stanley Cohen party for East Village shop Marisa Peluso x girlfriend, memorial poster for "lefty", 1994; 466986 (Box 14, Folder 057-N)
  - Junkies Suck grafitti, Stanley Cohen party for East Village shop Marisa Peluso x girlfriend, memorial poster for "lefty", 1994; 466985 (Box 7, Folder 057-P)
  - Police Commissioner Ray Kelly marching in St Pats parade, Steve Cannon host art opening at his legendary gallery Tribes, 1995; 466984 (Box 14, Folder 058-N)